Guide to the Workers Alliance of America Records, 1931-1999 AIS.2007.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Workers Alliance of America Records
1931-1999
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Workers Alliance of America
AIS.2007.03
8.7 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
The Workers Alliance of America (WAA) was formed in 1935 as a merger of predominantly socialist and communist-led unemployment councils, unemployment leagues and independent state organizations throughout the country. Soon after its inception, the FBI began to collect data on the Workers Alliance and its members. After a long court battle with the FBI, Eric Davin won the release of the Workers Alliance records with minimal redactions made to the files. Included in the collection are the originally released 1993-1994 FBI files and the 1996 court ordered Workers Alliance and Lasser files which outline the FBI's investigation of the Alliance and its president, as well as miscellaneous research and documents pertaining to the Organization as well as Lasser himself.
History
The Workers Alliance of America (WAA) was formed in 1935-1936 as a merger of predominantly socialist and communist-led unemployment councils, unemployment leagues and independent state organizations throughout the United States. At the head of the Workers Alliance was David Lasser, the organization's National President and Herbert Benjamin, its Secretary-Treasurer. Lasser, a registered Socialist, had graduated from Massachusetts Institute of Technology and served as editor of Technocracy Review and president of the American Interplanetary Society before becoming involved in labor issues and forming the Workers Unemployed League in New York in 1933. Benjamin joined the Communist Party after serving in World War I and worked as a party organizer. In 1931 he organized several Unemployed Councils which coordinated demonstrations on behalf of unemployed workers. The Workers Alliance claimed to be the spokesman for all Works Progress Administration employees and the unemployed, but by 1936 the Alliance had come to the attention of the FBI who began to monitor its actions.
Much of what is known about the Workers Alliance comes from their FBI file; however, because the FBI did not gather information on the group immediately, some early information was lost. The Workers Alliance held its Second National Convention in Washington, D.C. on April 7-10, 1936 where it incorporated the Communist-led Unemployment Councils into the organization and established its headquarters in New York. Other national conventions were held in Milwaukee (1937), Cleveland (1938), and Chicago (1940). The Workers Alliance quickly gained power and interest and, in 1938, claimed 800,000 members in 1400 local chapters. The Alliance started to fall apart in 1939 when membership began to decline with the introduction of a Works Progress Administration law prohibiting workers from membership in the Communist Party. Then, in 1940, Lasser resigned his presidency stating that the Workers Alliance was becoming too militant and dominated by the Communist Party, which claimed responsibility for the Alliance's creation and success. Benjamin also resigned at the 1940 National Convention, leaving the Alliance in the hands of inexperienced new officers. Although the Workers Alliance lost much of its prominence, the FBI investigation of the organization and its former members continued until 1961.
The Workers Alliance had several connections to the Pittsburgh area. Local chapters included: Wilkinsburg #4, McKeesport #29, Hazelwood #75, East Liberty #76, Turtle Creek #80, Pittsburgh #83, Homestead #108, and Lawrenceville #142. At the Alliance's Second National Convention, Pittsburgh sent fifty delegates, more than any other city and one less than the most represented states of New York and Pennsylvania (its only other delegate being from Bethlehem). Pittsburgh delegates included Joseph Remko, Peter Dougherty, John Hickey, and John Fagen. During the investigation, the FBI used Pittsburgh Sun Telegraph reporter Leo Sheridan as an informant to gain information about Workers Alliance president David Lasser while Lasser was in Harrisburg.
Scope and Content Notes
There are three types of files within the collection: copies of FBI documents, records relating to the court case between Eric Davin and the FBI, and records of Eric Davin's research into the Workers Alliance of America and David Lasser himself. Files related to the court case include correspondence between Davin and his attorneys at Reed Smith Shaw & McClay, which outline the legal measures taken on behalf of Davin and the defense, the FBI. Also included are random selections from the Workers Alliance FBI files which were used in an attempt to prove that excessive censorship had taken place and the defense's Vaughn Index which stated their explanation as to why each of these redactions was necessary. Court orders from the case are also present.
In 1996, the U.S. District Court for the Western District of Pennsylvania ruled that the FBI must reexamine and un-redact parts of the documents that did not fall under security laws and present a copy of the newly revised Workers Alliance and David Lasser files to Davin. Included in the collection are the entire 1993-1994 originally released FBI files and the 1996 court ordered Workers Alliance and Lasser files which outline the FBI's investigation of the Alliance and their president. By comparing the two sets of documents, one may note the amount of information concealed within the redactions of the original release. The documents also include a history of the Workers Alliance compiled by the FBI based on information received by informants and publications such as the Saturday Evening Post and Alliance newspapers and pamphlets.
Arrangement
Series I. Original FBI Documents Released to Eric Davin, 1992-1994
Series II. Eric Davin v. United States Department of Justice and Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1993-1998
Series III. Final Release of FBI Documents, 1996-1999
Series IV. Subject Files, 1931-1989
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Eric Davin on March 26, 2007. Additonal material acquired on October 31, 2014.
Previous Citation
Workers Alliance of America Records, 1931-1999, AIS.2007.03, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Records of the Workers Alliance of America, 1931-1999, UE/Labor 2007:03, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Existence and Location of Originals
The FBI National Headquarters and New York Office retain the original files regarding the Workers Alliance of America and David Lasser. The copies in this collection were made by the FBI for Eric Davin per his request in 1988 and the 1996 court order. Miscellaneous materials originated from various sources, acquired by Davin during his research.
Related Material
Federal Bureau of Investigation Files on the UE, UE 9-5, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Bibliography
High, Stanley. "Who Organized the Unemployed?" Saturday Evening Post. Vol.211 Issue 24. December 10, 1938:8-9, 30-36.
Unemployed -- United States -- Political activity; Depressions -- 1929; Pittsburgh (Pa.); New York (N.Y.); Communists -- United States; Unemployment -- United States; Social action; Labor unions -- United States; Labor; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation; United States. Works Progress Administration; Workers Alliance of America; United States. Freedom of Information Act; Benjamin, Herbert; Davin, Eric; Lasser, David
- Original FBI Documents Released to Eric Davin, 1992-1994; I.
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Section 4-7, undated (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Section 8-12, undated (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Section 13-16, undated (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Section 17-21, undated (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Section 22-30, undated (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Section 31-34, undated (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Section 35-43, undated (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Section 44, undated (Box 1, Volume 8)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI New York Office File 100-3638 Section 1-3, undated (Box 1, Volume 9)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI New York Office File 100-3638 Section 4, undated (Box 1, Volume 10)
  - David Lasser FBI File 121-413 Referrals, undated (Box 1, Volume 11)
  - Reprocessed Headquarters Release, undated (Box 1, Volume 12)
  - Cross References, undated (Box 1, Volume 13)
  - Government Agencies Correspondence with Eric Davin Regarding the Released Documents, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Davin Correspondence with FBI Headquarters, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Davin Correspondence with FBI New York Office, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Department of the Navy Processing Letter, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - US Office of Personnel and Management Letter & Documents, June 1992 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Davin Correspondence with US Department of Justice, 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "Conducting Research in FBI Records", 1990 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - US Department of State Letter & Documents, July 1992 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - USAID of State Letter & Documents, June 1992 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - URW 1939 Convention- LaCrosse Wisconsin, September 1939 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - 1992 Correspondence: Davin and Reed Smith Shaw & McClay (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Pittsburgh Papers covering Davin Lawsuit, April-June 1992 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Eric Davin v. United States Department of Justice and Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1993-1998; II.
  - Correspondence- Reed Smith Shaw & McClay, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Declaration of FBI Special Agent Robert A. Moran, December 2, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Memorandum of Law in Support of Defendant's Motion for Summary Judgment, December 17, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Exhibits 1&2 to Defendant's Motion for Summary Judgment, December 17, 1993 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Correspondence- Reed Smith Shaw & McClay, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Davin Appeals FBI Vaughn Index, August 1, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence- Reed Smith Shaw & McClay, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - First Quarter Representative Sample, December 29, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Second Quarter Representative Sample, January 29, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Defendant's Vaughn Index for the First and Second Quarter Samples, January, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Third Quarter Representative Sample, February 29, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Defendant's Vaughn Index for the Third Quarter Sample, February 29, 1996 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - Fourth Quarter Representative Sample, March 29, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Defendant's Vaughn Index for the Fourth Quarter Sample, March 29, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Defendant's Response to Plaintiff's Motion to Enforce the December 1, 1995 Court Order, March, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Plaintiff's Opposition to Defendant's Cross Motion for Entry of Scheduling and Protective Order, March, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Defendant's Motion for Summary Judgment, August 8, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Plaintiff's Response to Defendant's Motion for Summary Judgment, December 9, 1996 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - Exhibits to Plaintiff's Response to Defendant's Motion for Summary Judgment, December 9, 1996 (Box 2, Volume 4)
  - Plaintiff's Response to Defendant's Statement of Undisputed Material Facts, December 9, 1996 (Box 2, Volume 5)
  - Contested FBI Redactions among 500 Sampled Documents, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Brief for Appellees with Supplemental Index, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence- Reed Smith Shaw & McClay, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - FBI Documents, Government Exhibits #1-3 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper Clippings Regarding Eric Davin, 1994-1998 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous Davin Papers, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - FBI Rules and Regulations, 1937-1953 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "The Workers Alliance of America: The Organization of Relief Recipients" by Wilma Liebman, 1971 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Brief of Appellant Eric Davin, September 1994 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Documents from Reed Smith Shaw & McClay Regarding 1996 Motion to Enforce (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Appendices to 1994 Appeal (Box 6, Volume 1)
- Final Release of FBI Documents, 1996-1999; III.
  - History of the Workers Alliance of America, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Serials X1-45, undated (Box 6, Volume 2)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Serials 45-59, undated (Box 6, Volume 3)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Serials 60-79, undated (Box 6, Volume 4)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Serials 80-116, undated (Box 6, Volume 5)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Serials 117-125, undated (Box 6, Volume 6)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Serials 126-146, undated (Box 6, Volume 7)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Serials 146-170, undated (Box 6, Volume 8)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Serials 171-212, undated (Box 6, Volume 9)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Serials 213-226, undated (Box 4, Volume 1)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Serials 227-269, undated (Box 4, Volume 2)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Serials 269-318, undated (Box 4, Volume 3)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Serials 318X-346, undated (Box 4, Volume 4)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Serials 347-387, undated (Box 4, Volume 5)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Serials 388-438, undated (Box 4, Volume 6)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 61-7586 Sub A, undated (Box 4, Volume 7)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI File 47-13920, undated (Box 4, Volume 8)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI New York Office File 100-3638 Serials 1-136, undated (Box 4, Volume 9)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI New York Office File 100-3638 Serials 137-291, undated (Box 4, Volume 10)
  - Workers Alliance of America FBI New York Office File 100-3638 Serials 292-294 and 1A's, undated (Box 5, Volume 1)
  - New York Cross References, undated (Box 5, Volume 2)
  - David Lasser FBI File 61-HQ-10652, undated (Box 5, Volume 3)
  - David Lasser FBI File 121-HQ-413 Part I, undated (Box 5, Volume 4)
  - David Lasser FBI File 121-HQ-413 Part II, undated (Box 5, Volume 5)
  - David Lasser FBI File 124-HQ-2592 Part I, undated (Box 5, Volume 6)
  - David Lasser FBI File 124-HQ-2592 Part II, undated (Box 5, Volume 7)
  - Miscellaneous Lasser Documents, 1998 (Box 5, Volume 8)
  - Brief of Appellant Eric Davin, April 1998 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Circuit Court's FBI Victory Decision, September 1999 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Reed Smith Shaw & McClay Letter Regarding 1997 Appeal (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Subject Files, 1931-1989; IV.
  - Eric Leif Davin, "A Reply to Piven and Cloward" (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Lasser in New York Times Name Index (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Henry N. Dorris, "Workers Alliance Assailed" New York Times, June 1939 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Photocopies from New York Times, April 1941 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Excerpt from National Affairs section of Time, August 1936 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - David Lasser, Biographical Information (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Herbert Benjamin, Biographical Information (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Herbert Benjamin, References (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Page from National Affairs featuring picture of Lasser & Benjamin (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Partial Article on Dirksen by G.H. Mayer (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Lasser in Book Review Digest, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Article by Lasser in Congressional Digest, February 1939 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Davin Correspondences looking for David Lasser (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Davin Correspondence regarding "Wonder Stories" (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Digest of Phone Interview with David Lasser, April 1986 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Eric Davin, Interview with David Lasser, April 1986 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Interview with David Lasser (corrected), 1986 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Lasser Anthology Correspondences (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - William W. Bremer, "Along the 'American Way': The New Deal's Work Relief Programs for the Unemployed", December 1975 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Clara Severn, "We Begin to March", December 1934 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Marjorie R. Clark & S. Fanny Simon, "The Labor Movement in America", 1938 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - David Lasser, "Socialists and the Unemployed" American Socialist Monthly (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Museum of American Textile History Grants-in-Aid (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - William Gellerman, "Martin Dies", 1944 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - "Who was Who", Martin Dies Circled (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - "Freedom of Information- FBI Investigatory Records- Confidential Informant's Identity" Massachusetts Lawyers Weekly, February 1987 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - "WPA Sit-down" Business Week, October 1936 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - "The Common Welfare" The Survey, November 1936 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Joseph P. Kamp "Hunger March on Washington", February 1937 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Seldon Rodman, "Lasser and the Workers Alliance", September 1938 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - "Relief Ghosts Haunt State Capitols", May 1936 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Annual Bibliography of American Labor History, pp. 592-593, 598-599 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Bonnie Fox Schwartz, "The New Deal and Organized Labor: the CWA and the AFL Building Trades" Labor History v. 17 n. 1 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Walter Davenport, "Loyal Sons of WPA", October 1937 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Eric Hobsbawm, "Workers: Worlds of Labor", 1984 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Letter from US Department of Justice, January 1989 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Hearings on the Economic Security Act parts 9 & 11, February 1935 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Reference List on Old Age Pensions- Library of US Department of Labor (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Index of The Congressional Digest, vol. 14 no. 2, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Bibliographies Regarding Social Security/Welfare, July 1932- June 1937 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Book References to Technocracy Movement (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - James E. Sargent, "Roosevelt, the WPA Controversy, and the Workers Alliance of America", March 1982 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - "What President Roosevelt did to the Map of the U.S. in Four Years with $6,500,000,000" (Box 5, Folder 43)